it's gone global you're seeing it done
in every country my first encounter into
the mindset of a powerlifter occurred
when I was 24 years old so 18 years ago
back then I was doing heavy walking
barbell lunges I worked my way up to 225
pounds for 20 steps so 10 reps with each
leg and it was the hardest thing I've
ever done
it took me 14 minutes to recuperate to
be able to do the next set back then all
these articles were saying lunges are
for sissies and I'm like what are you
talking about this walking barbell
lunges the hardest thing ever and that's
when I first realized that power lifters
are not always very logical power
lifters care about four numbers they
care about their squat their bench their
deadlift in their total anything else is
irrelevant so it's okay to do lifts that
build those numbers but if they don't
it's not worth doing in their minds and
that's where you come up with their
terminology the main list and the
assistance lifts now what if you're a
female and you want nice boots that's
your number one goal well then should
the hip thrust be the main lift and
should everything else be assistance
less so let's not be fooled by
powerlifter terminology or power lift or
mindset I've seen all these big strong
men make fun of lunges and make fun of
hip thrusts but I'd like to see those
guys do a 225-pound for 20 step lunge
and do a 405 pound for 20 rep hit thrust
with good form do them both with good
form
and tell me what you feel afterwards if
you still think they're for [__] then
my hat sake you a bigger man recently I
saw a video on Facebook with Jim when
they're someone who I used to highly
respect and he was talking about how the
hip trust should not be a main lift you
can see the clip here so I was like you
know I read somewhere like when they're
like like every article on training is
pretty much the same it says hey make
sure you get your big potato a big steak
in right your squat bench deadlift press
row and then I saw hip thrust in there
and I was like when the [__] did this
happen like what point like what world
do I live in now where the hip thrust is
that's the same thing as a deadlift
I just got such a kick out of there now
this is disappointing for a number of
reasons
so remember listening to a podcast where
Jim weather was talking about how he can
no longer attire his shoes he asked to
have his wife help him put on his socks
and tie his shoes every morning and
that's from all his years of
powerlifting so why aren't we talking
more about this and why do competitive
power lifters try to have you go down
the same path as them when they're beat
to smithereens our goals for our clients
should be let's get them some glutes
let's give them some leg muscle but
let's keep their joints healthy and
prevent them from needing surgery so
they can keep lifting decade after
decade after decade if your goal is to
build glutes and you think of the lifts
that can help you reach your goals
it's gonna be hip thrust you know squats
deadlifts lunges back extensions
military press rows bench chin-ups those
don't help I love those lists and
they're a staple to me but make no
mistake about it the hip thrust is
numero uno
now why wouldn't hip thrust be a main
lift for men and women let's compare it
to a squat and deadlift you're moving a
huge load through a large range of
motion using a lot of muscles you can
hook up electrodes and measure EMG you
can see our force plate and measure
things like force power rate of force
development and work any way you slice
it the hip thrust is an amazing exercise
and most of all it's very well-suited
for progressive overload now sure you
have the idiots who screwed up don't
lock out or throw their chest up but the
same can be said for squats and
deadlifts an exercise is judged by how
it's done right not by the people who
screw it up but most important is the
safety of the hip thrust in 12 years of
prescribing the hip trusted clients I
haven't had a single injury not one in
12 years the same can be said for my
friend Jim Aaron and Blaine Bruno both
of them have coached thousands of people
in the last decade and have given hip
thrusts to almost all their clients and
they've never had an injury as well
here at glute lab we're going on almost
a year of being in business we're
training a couple hundred clients month
in and month out and we haven't had a
single injury here and the reason why is
because we do squats and deadlifts but
are not heavy barbell versions we do
lever squats goblet squats kettlebell
deadlifts lever deadlifts we do straddle
lifts but those are what we would call
assistance lists our main lifts here at
glute lab are the hip thrust the
straddle lifts the seated hip abduction
and the Nordic ham curl those are our
four main lifts and this is why we
haven't had a single injury and everyone
feels great here tests are easy to learn
they're well suited for every body type
in contrast some human bodies just
aren't well suited to squat or deadly
especially if you have relatively long
femurs for the squat or relatively short
arms for the deadlift
you're placing yourself greater injury
risk now I trained at a powerlifting gym
in Tempe Arizona called revolution
training systems for a couple of years
these guys were beasts but they were
always getting injured it just comes
with the territory I talked to Dave Tay
said it's just bound to happen if you're
squatting and dead lifting hundreds and
hundreds of pounds week in and week out
you're eventually gonna need a hip
replacement surgery a knee replacement
surgery you're gonna injure your back
that's the support of powerlifting
earlier this year I put out a survey and
almost 14,000 people answered that
survey and the general public isn't
fooled now power lifters and coaches and
other experts can try to fool people but
the general lifters know the truth
earlier this year I pulled thirteen
thousand six hundred ninety six lifters
now in this survey I asked what is your
favorite glute exercise and I had 16
different answers the number one
exercise was the hip thrust with 54%
squats got 6% deadlifts got 12% I asked
which exercise do you feel your glutes
working the hardest 77% picked the hip
thrust 4% the squat 7% the deadlift when
I asked which muscle is the limiting
factor when you hit the squat and
deadlift for the hip thrust 47% felt
that the glutes were the limiting factor
for the squad
six percent felt the glutes with a
limiting factor and for the deadlift 12
percent felt that their glutes when
asked which glute exercise felt the most
dangerous the responders chose the squat
as the most dangerous at thirty nine
percent compared to thirty three percent
for the deadlift and five percent for
the hip thrust 62 percent of responders
felt that the deadlift was the most
dangerous for the back followed by
twenty five percent for the squat and
three percent for the hip thrust forty
nine percent felt that the squat was the
most dangerous for the knees followed by
two percent for the deadlift and one
percent for the hip thrust when asked
which exercise is best at growing and
developing the glutes 68 percent chose
the hip thrust only five percent chose
the squat and five percent chose the
deadlift what's the primary reason why
people train the glutes 68 percent chose
for aesthetics and physique purposes
only six percent do so to transfer the
squat and deadlift 18 percent to improve
function and athletic performance and
eight percent to decrease pain in the
likelihood of injury so there you have
it the survey speaks for itself
so let's envision a world where the hip
thrust is the number one lift worldwide
it's the most popular exercise in the
world
what would we expect to see now this is
just my clients over the last year alone
I'm not talking about the other millions
of people who are doing hip thrusts this
is just what I've observed here at glute
lab in 2018
this is masa this is Jade this is Jax
here's Nikki here's Alexis this is Keanu
this is Dominic
here's Brie
[Music]
and this is obvious this is why you've
seen the rock do them several times on
his Instagram channel he loves the hip
thrust freakishly strong lifters like
Steffi Cohen and the Drina Savickas
they're doing their hip thrusts and they
feel like it transfers to their
powerlifting and you've also seen
professional sports players other actors
and actresses it's becoming very popular
it's gone global you're seeing it done
in every country now if you watch this
video and this doesn't make complete
total sense to you then what world do I
live in
[Music]